<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Musings, | Rasheed Bustamam Blogfolio]]></title>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/categories/musings/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-04T22:13:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://abustamam.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rasheed Bustamam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Important Truth for Creatives]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/04/important-truth-for-creatives/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T21:59:44-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/04/important-truth-for-creatives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are many important truths for creatives. The three most important truths to me are, “You are what you write,” “There is no such thing as a stupid idea,” and “Experiment with everything.” </p>

<p>Although I’d love to expand on all three truths, allow me to dive into the first one: “You are what you write.” </p>

<p>When we read a book by an author we aren’t familiar with, the only thing we know of the author is that he or she wrote the words on the pages. That is the only node of communication between author and reader. </p>

<p>The opinions expressed in the book may not necessarily be of the authors opinion. For example, a fiction book that glorifies the crime life does not necessarily mean that the author glorifies crime. It simply means that the author finds the subject of crime fascinating enough to warrant writing about it. </p>

<p>The interesting thing about writing is that in all cases, the reader gets a tiny glimpse of the inside of the writer’s mind. No matter what the piece is about, the resulting words on the page are manifestations of the ideas that were conjured by the writer. </p>

<p>As the writer, we are allowed the opportunity to choose what part of our minds we would like to expose; we are given the chance to choose which ideas we deem important enough to write about. </p>

<p>If we view our writings as an extension of our consciousness, then we don’t necessarily need to worry about critics. Some people like crime novels; some people hate crime novels. We never need to write for the people we know will hate our work, we simply write for the people we think will like our work. </p>

<p>By viewing our writings as a part of us, we are allowed to express ourselves in our writing in the same way we express ourselves in our speech or in our attire. Some people use slang, some people speak very formally. Some people dress in dark clothing, others dress in bright clothing. We never pay any mind to people who don’t like the way we dress, so we don’t need to pay any mind to people who don’t like the way we write. </p>

<p>But at the same time, it’s important to keep in mind the right message for the right audience. We wouldn’t show up to a wedding wearing the same clothes we’d wear to a birthday party. So it is important to keep in mind who our audience is, what our purpose is, and prepare to face the consequences that may arise for attempting to “break the norm.” </p>

<p>Perhaps the most important reason “You are what you write” is so important is that if we treat our writings as a part of ourselves, then we will respect our writings as much as we respect ourselves. If we expect our readers to respect our writings, we must first respect those same writings, just like we can’t expect people to respect us if we don’t respect ourselves. </p>

<p>If we hold respect for our writings, then we raise the bar for our own quality of writing, and in turn, we become better writers. Just like a pianist must practice a piece many many times before recital, we as writers must write many many times before publications. We see many books that have made authors famous, but what we don’t see is how many times that book has been written and rewritten and thrown in the trash before it was polished in to the gem we see on bookshelves. </p>

<p>By treating our writings with respect, we commit to our craft of writing by continually improving. I hope you respect yourself and your writing enough to commit to constant improvement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Audience]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/03/my-audience/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-03T22:05:17-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/03/my-audience</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s strange to think of myself as an authority figure. I view myself as a normal person going about every day life one day at a time.</p>

<p>However, as I pointed out before, I write to manifest my ideas into the real world. They may be ideas of philosophy or ideas of fictitious worlds. The ideas may mean nothing to the rest of the world, but to me, my ideas ARE my world.
So what am I an authority on? Well, on the non-fiction side, I can tell vivid stories that my words can bring to life. I told my coworkers the (true) story of me letting a spider live in my room. Such a simple story and yet, my coworkers still mention that story every so often.</p>

<p>I can uncover wisdom and life lessons from the most mundane concepts. Going back to my spider story, the moral there was that nothing is so insignificant in the world that is not worth mentioning. I learned that there are no boring “things,” just boring ideas.</p>

<p>And that is what I’m an authority on–creating magnificent ideas from seemingly “boring” things.</p>

<p>On the nonfiction side, my goal is to inspire, to encourage, to motivate, to teach. I believe that writing must make the world a better place, even if it is a world within the confines of one’s intellect. My ideal reader will ask of himself, “How is it that such a simple story can contain such profound meaning?”</p>

<p>If my ideal reader is to ask that, then my ideal goal is to keep my stories simple, but to twist them in a way that provides meaning beyond what most people expect from a simple story.</p>

<p>Fictionally speaking, I take my knack of real-life story telling and create an imaginary world and bring it to life. Even if the story is as far-fetched as wizards battling knights, I want it to be believable within the confines of the story. The world will have its own laws, similar to how our world has the laws of conservation of mass and the law of gravity. The story must adhere to these basic laws, but after the world is established, the characters in the world will shape the story.</p>

<p>I’m a fan of psychological thrillers. I never like cheap scares like pop-ups or screams; I prefer the type of thriller that keeps you on edge because the protagonist(s) and the antagonist(s) are trying to keep one step ahead of one another.</p>

<p>My ideal audience will be people who enjoy movies such as the Bourne series, and shows like Breaking Bad. Perhaps my writing will never reach the caliber of these wonderful films/shows, but I want to bend the mind of the reader. Just when the reader thinks one thing will happen, another thing happens and turns the story upside down.
In my fiction, I want to explore themes such as love and betrayal, but not so cliche as the femme fatale who ends up being the arch nemesis of the protagonist. In the real world, things are rarely binary–real people have real emotions that leave them conflicted and confused. What does a character do when faced with a moral dilemma where both options will hurt someone he loves?</p>

<p>I want to be an authority on the human psyche–explore why someone would cheat on their beloved, or murder their best friend. In addition, the writing will reflect the state of mind of the character in the spotlight, so readers can join the character in his metamorphosis.</p>

<p>To summarize, I want to be an authority on two things– manifesting profound lessons from mundane ideas, and creating characters that transform into completely different people. Through writing, I hope to grow into this authority and speak to the hearts of my readers.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Journey of Writing]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/journey-of-writing/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T00:23:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/journey-of-writing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Asking someone like me why I write is akin to asking someone why they drive. </p>

<p>Most people drive to go from point A to point B. There is something that is waiting for them at point B that warrants leaving point A. </p>

<p>Similarly, writing is my vehicle for reaching a new state of consciousness. Every word that I write is a step to reinvention. Reinvention for what, though? And what exactly is my point B? </p>

<p>In a world where change is the only thing that is constant, reinvention is necessary daily. If you aren’t keeping up with the ever-changing world, it will leave you behind. One way to keep up is to read. Another way to keep up is to write. Allow me to explain.</p>

<p>In order to write, we must first observe. Ideas must come from somewhere. It could be something as simple as a sunset, or as glorious as the aurora borealis. </p>

<p>When we really open your eyes to the world around you, and appreciate the beauty and perfection of everything, from the grasshoppers bouncing from one blade of grass to another, to the hundreds of people we don’t know and perhaps may never know, who take the same exact route as us to work, we begin to realize how insignificant we are. That guy who just took that last parking spot before you? He’s just like you. He has errands to run. Mouths to feed. He doesn’t know you, and you don’t know him. And it will likely stay that way because the world is bigger than you think. </p>

<p>By observing the world, and asking ourselves questions about why the world works a certain way, we can begin to form our own conclusions about how the world works. They don’t need to be scientific conclusions. Just theories and curiosity.</p>

<p>The formation of these ideas is incredibly important. Ideas are the key component of any piece worth reading. It’s necessary to become great at creating ideas that are worth writing about. And if you have no ideas worth writing about, then it’s even more crucial to make that idea worth writing about. </p>

<p>In yesterday’s piece, I argued that everything is inherently meaningless because the world is so vast, both in time and space, that nothing we do will ever matter. However, the beauty of life comes from the meanings we attribute to previously meaningless things. </p>

<p>The same goes for ideas–any idea can be worth writing about and expanding upon, only if you give it the meaning to become important. </p>

<p>A spider in my room is hardly an ingenious idea. In fact, there are very few ideas that could be more boring than that. However, through some observation and introspection, I gave that spider meaning to my life. Perhaps I even gave that spider meaning to other people’s lives. </p>

<p>And that is what I strive to do with my writing. I want to inspire readers. I want them to breathe meaning into previously meaningless things. I want to encourage them to slow down in the fast paced life, and sit outside, and observe the beautiful world around them. </p>

<p>That is my point B–inspiration. I write both to inspire myself, and to inspire others. </p>

<p>While I find my voice, I hope to be inspired by others taking the same journey as I am. I hope to forge lasting friendships and learn a lot from other people like me. </p>

<p>Conversely, I would also like to inspire others, and share mistakes I’ve made with other people like me.</p>

<p>I wish to join a community of passionate people full of ideas. We are all in the same journey, heading in the same direction, perhaps with a slightly different point B. But we’re all in the same vehicle, and as such, our combined powers will make us undefeatable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[And So I Write]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/01/and-so-i-write/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-01T00:22:45-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/01/and-so-i-write</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Who am I? Well, in the scheme of things, I’m a nobody. Probably not going to go down in history for anything worthwhile.</p>

<p>And I’m perfectly fine with that.</p>

<p>99% (that’s a low estimate) of all people in the world are nobodies; people who, a century after their death, will be lost in the myriad of databases. People whose entire life’s work will be meaningless and not have contributed anything to the society of the future. Nobodies who strive daily to accumulate things that won’t even last for fifty years.</p>

<p>Despite that depressing thought, being a “nobody” is beautiful. Being able to attribute meaning to a seemingly meaningless existence is simply incredible. For the billions and billions of nobodies who exist, and have existed, in this world, what makes life worth living? Why do we wake up every day, knowing that it won’t matter in a hundred years? Why do we bother going through the monotony of daily life considering that our days are not even a blip on the radar of the wheel of time?</p>

<p>I can tell you only from the perspective of this one “nobody” among billions.</p>

<p>First, I believe nothing is truly meaningless. We’ve given meaning to seemingly random lines and squiggles on paper, that we now call text. Depending on the font, the lines and squiggles may look completely different but they still convey the same meaning.</p>

<p>Going further, though the meaning of those lines and squiggles may be obvious, the way those lines and squiggles are organized and shaped could express even deeper meaning. We have the iconic “f” symbol–a tiny box taking less than a square-inch of space on paper says instantly– “we’re on Facebook!”</p>

<p>And that’s exactly how I view my life. Everything in life has meaning, if I take the time to give it meaning.</p>

<p>Just two weeks ago, I decided to allow a spider to take residence in a corner of my room. It was just a spider, among countless other spiders–spiders that I usually kill. But I decided to try something new, and did not kill the spider.</p>

<p>Every couple days he would disappear, but he would come back, until yesterday I saw his curled up body under his web.</p>

<p>The spider was inherently meaningless. His short life means nothing in the scheme of things. It didn’t matter that I had decided not to kill him that one day–two weeks later, he would already be dead, and nothing would have changed.</p>

<p>Yet that spider meant a lot to me. Its prolonged existence meant that I was letting go of an irrational fear that millions of people around the world have. It made me wonder why we humans feel it is perfectly fine to destroy spiders’ nests–nests that are beautifully constructed and take its artists sometimes its entire life to build?</p>

<p>It made me question what we would do if a higher being viewed human existence as insignificant as humans view arachnid existence. How we would react if the higher being destroyed our technology the same way we destroy spider nests.</p>

<p>The world will continue to turn, with or without humans; with or without spiders. And yet, as long as spiders exist, they will continue to build their nests; as long as humans exist, we will continue to push the envelope of what is possible.</p>

<p>And that’s where I fit in. I may not be inventing a brand new car, or rocket ship, or mobile device. I’m simply inventing new things in my life. Learning languages, learning programming, satiating my curiosity for the world around me, breaking the boundaries of what I thought was possible for myself, and most importantly, using those random lines and squiggles to communicate my findings with the world. The continuous challenge to be challenged drives me to wake up and carpe diem every morning.</p>

<p>Every day, “I love you”s are exchanged between couples, parents and children, siblings, etc. Three seemingly random utterances of the breath that can have such a profound effect on someone’s life. Three words that can mean the difference between life and death for a depressed individual, or the difference between feeling special and feeling neglected for a child. Even though these words have no meaning in most other languages, they are among the most powerful words in the English language. The fact that this small utterance could have such a profound meaning that it could make or break a relationship is possibly the most beautiful thing about human beings.</p>

<p>I’m perfectly fine with my meaningless existence. But the meaning I have given my life is all the meaning that is necessary for me. I hope you join me in my journey to discover and add more meaning to life. And so I write…</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
