<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mongodb, | Write Bright]]></title>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/categories/mongodb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-19T22:04:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://abustamam.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rasheed Bustamam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kickstarting Your First MEAN Web App With Yeoman]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2015/08/19/kickstarting-your-first-mean-web-app-with-yeoman/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T21:42:32-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2015/08/19/kickstarting-your-first-mean-web-app-with-yeoman</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been going through <a href="http://www.freecodecamp.com">Free Code Camp</a> and after finishing the front-end “ziplines” (which require a writeup of their own, eventually) I’m finally getting set for the fullstack “basejumps.”</p>

<p>However, on their <a href="http://www.freecodecamp.com/challenges/waypoint-get-set-for-basejumps">“Get Set” module</a>, I ran into some problems with Cloud9 (primarily the memory issue), so I decided to figure out how to do some of these things on my local machine.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>This is primarily a document for me to refer to when I create more fullstack apps, but may as well share it.</p>

<p>Note that I am using OS X. I provide no guarantees in this document, as I’m writing it as it worked for me. Feel free to leave a comment though.</p>

<h2 id="step-0-get-your-environment-set-up">Step 0: get your environment set up</h2>

<p>You should have the following installed: <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">npm</a>, <a href="http://brew.sh">Homebrew</a>, and probably <a href="http://www.bower.io">bower</a>. Follow the links to install them.</p>

<p>Next, you should install <a href="https://github.com/creationix/nvm">nvm</a> by running the following script in your terminal:</p>

<p>using curl:
<code>curl -o- https://raw.githubusercontent.com/creationix/nvm/v0.26.0/install.sh | bash</code></p>

<p>or Wget:
<code>wget -qO- https://raw.githubusercontent.com/creationix/nvm/v0.26.0/install.sh | bash</code></p>

<p>The stablest node is <code>node v0.12.7</code> as of this writing.</p>

<p>I’m going to assume that you are in your project directory now. My project directory is <code>/sample</code> so keep that in mind going forward.</p>

<h2 id="step-1-get-yeoman-started-up">Step 1: Get Yeoman started up</h2>

<p>Copy this into your terminal:</p>

<p><code>echo "export NODE_PATH=$NODE_PATH:/usr/local/lib/node_modules" &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc &amp;&amp; source ~/.bashrc &amp;&amp; npm install -g yo grunt grunt-cli generator-angular-fullstack &amp;&amp; yo angular-fullstack</code></p>

<p>This will install grunt, grunt-cli, and yeoman’s Fullstack Angular generator.</p>

<p>If the installs go well, Yeoman will start up and it will ask you questions. Answer as follows (feel free to answer however you want, but this is how I did):
```
What would you like to write scripts with? JavaScript</p>

<p>What would you like to write markup with? HTML</p>

<p>What would you like to write stylesheets with? CSS</p>

<p>What Angular router would you like to use? ngRoute</p>

<p>Would you like to include Bootstrap? Yes</p>

<p>Would you like to include UI Bootstrap? Yes</p>

<p>Would you like to use MongoDB with Mongoose for data modeling? Yes</p>

<p>Would you scaffold out an authentication boilerplate? Yes</p>

<p>Would you like to include additional oAuth strategies? Twitter</p>

<p>Would you like to use socket.io? No</p>

<p>May bower anonymously report usage statistics to improve the tool over time? (Y/n) Y
```</p>

<p>If the last step fails (the <code>bower install</code> and <code>npm install</code>) then run it manually:</p>

<p><code>bower install &amp;&amp; npm install</code></p>

<h2 id="step-2-install-mongodb">Step 2: Install MongoDB</h2>

<p>This part was complicated. But here we go.</p>

<p>First, install MongoDB (I used Homebrw):</p>

<p><code>brew install mongodb</code></p>

<p>IF all goes well, type the following into your terminal:</p>

<p><code>mkdir data &amp;&amp; echo 'mongod --dbpath=data --nojournal --rest "$@"' &gt; mongod &amp;&amp; chmod a+x mongod</code></p>

<p>Note that the Free Code Camp tutorial has this extra line: <code>--bind_ip=$IP</code>, which didn’t work on my machine. I will find out soon enough if omitting it causes any problems.</p>

<p>Now, to start your database, just run…</p>

<p><code>./mongod</code></p>

<p>Easy as pie.</p>

<h2 id="step-3-start-your-server">Step 3: Start your server</h2>

<p>This one is easy:</p>

<p><code>grunt serve</code></p>

<p>A new window should automatically open up with Yeoman saying “Allo Allo!”</p>

<p>That’s as far as I am now, I will continue updating this document as I build my first fullstack project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
