<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: 500wed, | Rasheed Bustamam Blogfolio]]></title>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/categories/500wed/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-16T09:32:54-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://abustamam.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rasheed Bustamam]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 22: Topoi Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/22/day-22-topoi-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-22T23:05:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/22/day-22-topoi-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Day 22: Reach back into your Topoi from these past few days, pick a topic to address, and write!</strong></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 21: Geothe's Walking Stick Pt 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/21/day-21-geothes-walking-stick-pt-5/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-21T23:04:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/21/day-21-geothes-walking-stick-pt-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Day 21: Again today, for the final Topoi day, return to your past writing and Goethe’s Walking Stick…(See description)</strong></p>

<p><em>Again today, for the final Topoi day, return to your past writing and Goethe’s Walking Stick and ideas you’ve developed so far in the Topoi: who you are, what you want our of your writing, whom you hope to speak to, the ideas you’ve written down in your Goethe’s Walking Stick, and the questions you’ve asked. Find more concepts and ideas you’re interested in writing about. Then… - Work those ideas through your own Topoi, asking questions today about Values. - Write down as many questions as you can think of that belong to Values. - Choose one question to address today, one you think is truly, terribly, wonderfully interesting, interesting enough to captivate an audience you hope to speak to. - Finally, address that question.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 20: Goethe's Walking Stick Pt 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/20/day-20-goethes-walking-stick-pt-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-20T23:03:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/20/day-20-goethes-walking-stick-pt-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Day 20: Again today, return to your first week of writing, to your Goethe’s Walking Stick… (See description.)</strong></p>

<p><em>Again today, return to your first week of writing, to your Goethe’s Walking Stick, and to the ideas you’ve developed so far in the Topoi. Page through the ideas there: who you are, what you want our of your writing, whom you hope to speak to, the ideas you’ve written down in your Goethe’s Walking Stick, the questions you’ve asked. Find more concepts and ideas you’re interested in writing about. Then… - Work those ideas through your own Topoi, asking questions today about Form &amp; Structure. - Write down as many questions as you can think of that belong to Form &amp; Structure. - Choose one question to address today, one you think is truly, terribly, wonderfully interesting, interesting enough to captivate an audience you hope to speak to. - Finally, address that question.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 19: Goethe's Walking Stick Pt 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/19/day-19-goethes-walking-stick-pt-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-19T23:02:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/19/day-19-goethes-walking-stick-pt-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Day 20: Again today, return to your first week of writing, to your Goethe’s Walking Stick… (See description.)</strong></p>

<p><em>Again today, return to your first week of writing, to your Goethe’s Walking Stick, and to the ideas you’ve developed so far in the Topoi. Page through the ideas there: who you are, what you want our of your writing, whom you hope to speak to, the ideas you’ve written down in your Goethe’s Walking Stick, the questions you’ve asked. Find more concepts and ideas you’re interested in writing about. Then… - Work those ideas through your own Topoi, asking questions today about Form &amp; Structure. - Write down as many questions as you can think of that belong to Form &amp; Structure. - Choose one question to address today, one you think is truly, terribly, wonderfully interesting, interesting enough to captivate an audience you hope to speak to. - Finally, address that question.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day 18: Goethe's Walking Stick Pt 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/day-18-goethes-walking-stick-pt-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-18T23:01:19-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://abustamam.github.io/blog/2014/10/18/day-18-goethes-walking-stick-pt-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Day 18: Again today, return to your first week of writing and to your Goethe’s Walking Stick. (See description.)</strong></p>

<p><em>Again today, return to your first week of writing and to your Goethe’s Walking Stick. Page through the ideas there: who you are, what you want our of your writing, whom you hope to speak to, the ideas you’ve written down in your Goethe’s Walking Stick, etc. Find concepts and ideas you’re interested in writing about. Then…   - Work those ideas through your own Topoi, asking questions today about Change.  - Write down as many questions as you can think of that belong to Change.  - Choose one question to address today, one you think is truly, terribly, wonderfully interesting, interesting enough to captivate an audience you hope to speak to.  - Finally, address that question.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
